<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two new sermons preached in Oxford, fitted for these times the one of diuine mysteries, the other of church-schismes, but the vnity of orthodox professors / by J.D.</title>
            <author>Doughty, John, 1598-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20670</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23659459</idno>
  <idno type="VID">26776</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248529681</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 7072.1</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S4614</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20670)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26776)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1831:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two new sermons preached in Oxford, fitted for these times the one of diuine mysteries, the other of church-schismes, but the vnity of orthodox professors / by J.D.</title>
                  <author>Doughty, John, 1598-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26, 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also published under title: A discourse concerning the abstrusivenesse of divine mysteries.</note>
                  <note>"With speciall licence."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi] A-F⁴ G².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XII-XVI --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">God --  Knowableness --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Schism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26776:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26776:1"/>
            <p>TWO NEW SERMONS, PREACHED IN <hi>OXFORD,</hi> fitted for these times.</p>
            <p>The one of Diuine Mysteries: The other of Church-Schismes, <hi>but the Ʋnity of Orthodox</hi> PROFESSORS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>With speciall. Licence.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for, <hi>M. S.</hi> 1629.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26776:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26776:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CONCERNING</hi> DIVINE MYSTERIES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ROM. 12. VER. 16.</bibl>
                  <p>Be not wise in your owne conceipts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT to trouble you with any tedious Preface: The Romanes here in this Chapter may seeme vpon their new enlightning by the Gospell, not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue vsed those spirituall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments which they did therewith receiue. For otherwise not long since they were a people of all most reprobate; so farre from the light of Grace, that they became even void of common sense: What the <hi>Satyrist</hi> speaketh concerning Eunuchs in that they are dismembred,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quarit se natura, nec invenit</hi>—</l>
                  <note place="margin">Petronius.</note>
               </q> might be affirmed of them in a more proper phrase; they had by custome of sinne lost the very principles of reason: doing those things (saith the Apostle) <hi>which are against nature.</hi> Rom. 1. 26. But now at length through an especiall calling by God's grace, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26776:3"/> were well rid of that wretched estate in which they lay; being insteed thereof indued with many rare gifts both of the will &amp; vnderstanding; like men therefore newly recouered from out the dungeon into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable sunshine, they doe not moderately enioy this so vnwonted a light, but with too much exultancie: they wax proud and high minded: Before they sinned in not knowing God or what was right, &amp; now they take an occasion of transgressing from the abundance of their knowledge; As the Apostle speakes of leaven 1. Cor. 5. that <hi>a little of it leaueneth the whole lumpe:</hi> so here chiefly by a little selfe-conceipt of knowledge, all their other graces are in danger to be corrupted.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> therefore to coole and allay this heat of ambition is very diligent: first he adviseth them in the 6. v. aboue to measure themselues by their proper en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments: whither (saith he) you haue receaued the gift of <hi>Prophecie,</hi> vse <hi>prophecie,</hi> or of <hi>ministring,</hi> waite vpon your <hi>ministery:</hi> In the beginning of this 16<seg rend="sup">th</seg> v. he biddeth them not to <hi>minde high things:</hi> not things which might serue rather to increase their tumour, then build them vp in the spirit. And lastly he presseth them with the words of my Text. <hi>Be not wise, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where may you be pleased to obserue two maine<note place="margin">Division.</note> parts: first a wisdome forbidden: and then what wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it is: The wisdome here inhibited may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, either in regard of the <hi>obiect,</hi> as <hi>Be not wise,</hi> that is, be not overcurious to prye into secrets vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed:<note place="margin">Iustin. in Comment.</note> In which sense I will handle; first, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundnesse of Divine Mysteries: 2<seg rend="sup">ly</seg>, the danger if any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26776:3"/> shall presse too farre into them; or you may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it in respect of the <hi>subiect,</hi> as <hi>Be not wise,</hi> that is be not conceiptedly lift vp in minde. Wherevpon I shall consider the weaknesse of humane knowledge; &amp; how at leastwise it is not our owne, but from God: Out of the second generall, whereas it is denied that we should bee <hi>wise in our owne conceipts,</hi> a rule or square may be thence supposed, according to which we may be wise, and that I define to bee either <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> or <hi>Revelation.</hi> Of these in their order, and first of the profoundnesse of <hi>Divine Mysteries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So deepe are most points of this art, that in truth<note place="margin">P. 1.</note> they are aboue the lawfulnesse of mans search. The Apostle in the precedent Chap: at the 33 v. tearmes them not <hi>incomprehensible,</hi> but rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things not to be inquired into: such as must bee reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced and admired in silence; <hi>Quod non potest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendi</hi> (saith <hi>Lactantius) nec quari debet:</hi> if myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cannot be sounded by vs, neither ought they at all to be discussed; It is true that whatsoeuer may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to our happinesse, the Lord hath revealed most gratiously; he hath giuen vs his word to bee our guid and comfort; For as the Israelites were in the vast Wildernesse, so are we beset with sinnes and errours in this world: as they then iournied towards the earthly Canaan through conduct of those two <hi>pillars</hi> Exod: 13. v. 21. so may we walke safely on towards the heauenly by the guidance of his double Testament; Nothing there is that may help to further vs, but it is either in both, or in one of them imparted: But as for high and sublime <hi>mysteries</hi> the Lord hath greatly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26776:4"/> concealed them; hee hath as it were close lockt them vp: For suppose he did communicate and lay them open, they would not so much instruct our saithes, as amaze our iudgements. Flashes and strictures of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doe indeed enlighten the eye, but by reason of too subtile a nature they doe also hurt it: euen so my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries too abstract are apt to dazle the weaknesse of reason, if they were presented vnto vs.</p>
            <p>There are I confesse degrees of knowledge: the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall man vnderstands a great deale more then the carnall: his eyes be newly <hi>vnscaled</hi> by grace, as once S. <hi>Pauls</hi> were: but it is touching matters of saluation or faith: as for these hidden and abstruse points he is still dim-sighted. In the 5<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of the Apoc. v. 2. tis said, <hi>who is able to open the bookes</hi> who <hi>but the Lyon of the tribe of Iuda?</hi> It is meant of the booke in which such secrets lie coucht, and infolded; where you may note, that wee, nay the best of God's Saints, are so vnfit to expound the contents, that wee may not so much as vntie the claspes.</p>
            <p>Now the reason of this may be, both mans dulnes, and the abstractnesse of these points; as for man, he is of an vnderstanding much darkned: what it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fall, whither as of a <hi>Viator,</hi> or a <hi>Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor,</hi> or mixt as <hi>Aquinas Sum: P. 1<seg rend="sup">a</seg>, Q.</hi> 104. resolueth, it matters not: but certainely he did not then apprehend supernaturall things more fully, then since hee doth scarcely and with dimnesse; As the earth is, so are the earthly, of a dull and heauy capacitie, reason here hardly raising it selfe aboue the sense; <hi>David</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth in this regard that he was <hi>ignorant,</hi> nay <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:26776:4"/> and as <hi>a beast,</hi> Psal. 73. Now on the otherside di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine mysteries, whither they concerne God in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or in his attributes, they are very sublime.</p>
            <p>First God in his essence he is so pure, that he is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and abstractnesse it selfe: as the eie be it neuer so cleere cannot see the thinnesse of the ayre: so neither can the eie of the minde truely imbrace the purenesse of the Dictie, because wanting as 'twere a solid sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance wherevpon to fix; And therefore you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue how alwaies it falls downe streight vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts<note place="margin">Anon: E<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de Cardinal: Christ. operib.</note> more grosse and earthly; <hi>Cum accesser<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (saith one) <hi>longius abit,</hi> God the neerer wee labour to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him, the farther wee shall finde him remoued beyond our search; The <hi>Poet</hi> some where brings in <hi>Aeneas</hi> catching earnestly at <hi>Cre<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sa's</hi> ghost, but that flying and escaping betweene his embraces: wee may puzle much about the diuine essence; but euen then when wee thinke to haue laid hold on it, it proues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehensible; say <hi>I am that I am</hi> is my name, was once the instruction of God vnto <hi>Moses,</hi> Exod. 3. v. 14. and let him be still what he is? it is impossible that hee should be measured by mans weake braine.</p>
            <p>Much lesse may that sacred diuision of the Trinity be perceiued; how three persons are as it were graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon one and the same essence: what the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vrge by way of similitude from the vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, memory, and will, doth but badly illustrate the cause; for if the <hi>Father</hi> begot the <hi>Sonne</hi> as the power of the vnderstanding produceth its act, then must the <hi>Sonne</hi> beget another <hi>Sonne</hi> as being with the same power indued: likewise as the <hi>Spirit</hi> is produced by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26776:5"/> loue, so shall it produce againe a <hi>Spirit</hi> by loue; wherefore this instance fals short of a due resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance: Yet is it I confesse the best helpe and shadowe for expression that either here wee haue or may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: Whilst <hi>Moses</hi> kept vnvailed, the Israelites could<note place="margin">Exod. 34.</note> not indure to look vpon his face it was so bright; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may wee behold this mystery vnlesse it bee through such shadowes and that but weakly; So then that which <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath here defined, is most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably<note place="margin">Apolog.</note> true: <hi>Deum astimari facit dum aestimari non capit:</hi> wee doe best apprehend God either in his es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, or in the Trinity, if we confesse that we cannot.</p>
            <p>Come now to those attributes of his power, his will, and such like; what man is able possibly to reach them? Who doth not streight acknowledge his dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? So long as the vnderstanding meets with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects equall and befitting it's strength, it doth well enough; but the hand you knowe cannot graspe a thing bigger then it selfe: neither can a finite appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension throughly conceaue those properties, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infinite: it doth well conceaue that they are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite but not the infinitenesse; <hi>hee is as high as heauen what can'st thou doe? deeper then hell what canst thou knowe?</hi> Iob. 11. v. 8. By the power indeed of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty was this round world framed; his arme and strength laid the foundation of it, no man doubts: but cleerely to apprehend the manner of its production, requires more then a finite capacity; our vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is not able to passe ouer so vast a distance, as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth betweene an vtter nothing, and the newnesse of a being. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes it an act of faith to perceiue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26776:5"/> this, <hi>Through faith wee vnderstand that the worlds were framed,</hi> Heb. 11. 3.</p>
            <p>Yet especially are those mysteries of his will and decree most abstruse; for they be not only abstract in their owne nature, but also concealed by God of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, <hi>No man knoweth the things of a man saue the spirit of man which is in him,</hi> 1. Cor. 2. <hi>And a prudent man</hi> (saith <hi>Solomon) concealeth his knowledge,</hi> Prov. 12. v. 23. Now God is all wisdome, and for this must be as secret in his determinations, as he is iust and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; whither he reprobates men absolutely, or vpon a presupposed fall, seemes a question of a perplext dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty: Againe, whither he allowes sufficiency of grace to all or not, 'tis easier to argue, then finde out wherevpon to pitch a setled assent. The Aegyptians to declare the abstrusenesse of their rites did place vpon the forefront of their Temples the picture of a <hi>Sphynx:</hi> how much more iustly may wee doe so? So many scruples doe occurre in the bulke of diuinity, which if they be searched vnto the bottome, they far surmount humane reach.</p>
            <p>I let passe here that <hi>great mystery</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> calls it) of Christ's being incatnate; that of the <hi>last re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing</hi> of our bodies, both which for their seeming impossibility, were points in times past which ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter professors of the Christian faith did most hardly digest; humane reason proued so incapable to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, that they became vnto it a rock of offence: Neither stand I to inlarge those disputes of the <hi>worlds consummation,</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> with others, not so rightly to bee tearm'd doubts as riddles; Not the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26776:6"/> Angels themselues perchance do comprehend them, as being of that rancke into which they doe but <hi>peepe</hi> as before they did into that of the redemption of mankinde. <hi>Mirandula</hi> in his Apologie much extolleth certaine <hi>Cabalisticall</hi> volumes which he had, as if in them all such mysterious doctrines had beene darkly comprized; for (saith he) besides the holy writ, God did so provide that whatsoeuer is to be known, might out of these be collected by the more wise and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iewes: which his opinion he groundeth vpon Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras. Esdr, 2. 14. This is but a meere fancy, yet so farre it agreeth to right, that by it is intimated the abstruse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of diuine truthes; <hi>Out of whose womb commeth the yee</hi> (saith the Lord) Iob. 38. or, <hi>hast thou entred into the treasures of snowe?</hi> If not into those naturall storehouses of yce &amp; hayle, much lesse can we ascend into those spirituall ones of which I speak: Doubtlesse they are more remoued, and being heauenly they as farre exceed the compasse of mans wit, as the heauen is diuided from the earth.</p>
            <p>Neither bee these alone of chiefest moment so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volued, but lesser also and those which we perhaps do iudge our selues to vnderstand compleatly; But that of <hi>Gods prouidence</hi> &amp; the administration of the world, may seeme to haue stagger'd the kingly Prophet: how the wicked should still flourish, and the righteous bee<note place="margin">Psal. 23.</note> daily afflicted: the manner of the soules beginning, whither propagated or infused, did much trouble <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> and <hi>Hierom; Caliginosissima quaestio</hi> (saith <note n="*" place="margin">Austin.</note> one of them) it is a question too intricate; not to heape vp many: <note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 2.</note>
               <hi>Arnobius</hi> in the controuersie, <hi>why God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26776:6"/> sinne,</hi> sith he hates it, yeeldeth himselfe in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner blanckt.</p>
            <p>If any shall aske why divine truthes are so obscur'd, it may bee they are reserued to augment our future blisse, which shall consist as well in the enlargement of our knowledge, as the refining of our wills: when the vaile of ignorance is to be taken away, and <hi>wee shall knowe even as we are knowne,</hi> 1. Cor. 13. or perhaps it is to encrease the state and respect of them; for men doe vsually esteeme that with greater reverence, with which they bee not so throughly acquainted. Vpon this ground the heathen also did, (as <hi>Macrobius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serues)<note place="margin">In so<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Scip L. 1.</note> couch their religion vnder darke types; thence so many fables and seeming toyes: with reverence to this policy, some heretiques likewise had their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to that of the Apocal. 2. 24</p>
            <p>Howsoever, as long as wee remaine clothed with<note place="margin">Durand<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this corruptible flesh, we be in such mysterious points but weakly grounded; we haue onely <hi>assensum fidei</hi> an easie beleife, not <hi>assensum scientia,</hi> a peircing knowledge; Religion is not as other sciences, it sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth and takes vpon trust very much: which gaue occasion long since to the blasphemous Pagans to deride it as a groundlesse fabricke of the braine: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues much and knoweth little, yea knowledge it selfe here is but a kinde of practicke beleife: <hi>If any man will doe (Gods) will, hee shall knowe of his doctrine,</hi> Iohn 17. v. 17. Take but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for an instance, a man of rare excellency; one who had beene wrapt vp aboue the heauens and himselfe: yet (as himselfe doth imply) he heard those things in his rapture, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26776:7"/> he did not well conceaue; nay in the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Iewes reiection, and calling of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, when he hath driuen it to a head as neere as hee can, he meets with a sea vnfordable; hee is faine to sit downe as it were vpon the banke, and cry out, <hi>O the depth of the wisdome and knowledge of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude this point with the words of the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storian;<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> that which he speaks of state misteries, may of these be more fitly pronounced, <hi>Non aliter ratio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stat, quàm si vai redd<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur:</hi> it is the priuiledge of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine mysteries, that they be vnderstood of God alone. As for others, a bold enquiry here, is not more in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent, then full of <hi>danger</hi> and hazard, Which is my second point.</p>
            <p>When men walke vpon prerupt and steepe places, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> they are subiect to full; and so here by medling with these high points, an errour or heresie is quickly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred; yet such is the intemperate desire of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that men cannot bee bounded in the search thereof, Even our first parents in Paradise were not free from this itch; where when all the trees besides<note place="margin">De orthodox. religionc. L 4.</note> were granted them for vse, they must needs tast the excepted fruit, which (as <hi>Nicetas Chomates</hi> imagineth) was nothing but an allegory or figure of knowledge. Hence in their posterity such lusting after nouelties: such an vnsatiate curiosity. In truth to asswage this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in part, the Lord hath wholly exposed all the creatures to mans disquiry; as it is said of the Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, Psalm. 104. that God hath made the <hi>wide Sea</hi> for him to <hi>play in,</hi> that is to expatiate and take his swinge; so hath he as it were made this lower world
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26776:7"/> for mans delight and contemplation; he may roue as, he list, and not only rest in the outside of things, but also lawfully diue into the in most essence.</p>
            <p>But for <hi>Divine mysteries,</hi> if we presse too farre, we become obnoxious to errors &amp; slips; for from whence sprang heresies of old in the Christian world, but from this fountaine? Whilst men in the search of truth were directed rather by too much ambition, then an aduised modesty; whilst they would needs be tampering beyond their skill in points of the chiefest moment. Hence is it that wee finde more heresies to haue arisen concerning those two greatest mysteries of the <hi>Trinitie</hi> and <hi>incarnation,</hi> then about all the rest: Arians, Nestorians, yea most sects did slumble at these blocks: The stomacke when it meeteth with meats hard and not well to bee digested, it sends vp noxious vapours into the braine: euen so these men lighting vpon points which were too knotty for them, and not being guided by discretion, insteed of doctrines broached their wild conceipts: For this cause wee finde the Fathers euermore cautelous and very retir'd. Read but S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Hilary</hi> in his 2. l. See before the entrance of his dispute concerning the Trinity, how he puts on, and then falls backe, venters againe and recoyleth as fast: <hi>mihi</hi> (saith he) <hi>in sensu labes, in intelligentiâ stupor est:</hi> both my sense and reason are astonisht. The good Father may seeme rather to haue feared a surreptitious curiosity, then if he should<note place="margin">Gelasius Cucycenus.</note> bluntly haue betrai'd the cause. At the Synod of Nice where the same point was debated, the Bishops there expresly reiected the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: vndertake
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26776:8"/> they would to proue the mysterie, but for the manner they durst not.</p>
            <p>Such was their religious diffidence in these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and such others also; to whom I could wish that the Schoolemen were not vnlike. But contrariwise what arrogancy doth wholy possesse them? How re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectlessely doe they thrust into the most hidden se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets? It was a time when the Lord gaue command, Exod. 19. v. 12. that none, neither man nor beast should <hi>touch</hi> the mount where himselfe was. And surely there is great reason why the same edict should bee proclaim'd againe: this boldnes of some wits calling too nicely into dispute, those mysteries, which are more iustly to be adored; Euer and anon they discusse the absolutenesse of their makers power: what may be effected by it, and what not: sometimes they argue his freedome and will, and happily limit it with some vaine distinction: Nay so audacious are many, that except they sport themselues in these mysteries they be not contented; witnesse for instance sake those queries, whither God be <hi>materia prina,</hi> and, whither <hi>Christs divinitie might not suppositate a fly:</hi> which &amp; such like doe not informe the minde, but truly wrong the maiestie of God: so that here I could almost ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud that sharp censure of iudicious <hi>Calvin,</hi> though in another case: <hi>Scholae in deterius semperaberrant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Instit. l. 3.</note> the Schoolmen do alwaies incline to the worse hand.</p>
            <p>Neither in this are the Arminians lesse to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: <hi>Who hath been his counsellour?</hi> saith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet concerning God, Isa. 40. 13. Whom among the sonnes of men did he choose for his assistant? But they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26776:8"/> as confidently state those his Acts of election and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, as if they had themselues decreed them: they soare vp on high euen into the bosome of the Almighty: men oftimes of greater reach in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies, then of wisdome or discreetnesse. Our Saviour once tooke vp <hi>Peter,</hi> Ioh. 21. 21. but for that frivolous question: <hi>What shall this man doe?</hi> Hee is offended with the Disciples for inquiring too narrowly after the <hi>restauration</hi> of the Iewish estate, Act. 1. 6. how much more is it to be feared that hee will sharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke those forenamed intruders, if they learne not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to curb their knowledge; <hi>Austin</hi> in one of his Epistles, hath a pretty allusion of a certaine passenger falne perchance into a pit: <hi>Obsecro</hi> (saith hee there so falne to one comming to his rescue) <hi>quomodò hinc me liberes, non quomodo huc ceciderim quaeras:</hi> stand not to expostulate with me how I slipt in, but rather kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly helpe me out: We are all falne through <hi>Adam</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a wide gulfe of vnhappinesse; let vs endeauour to recouer our selues: let vs examine rather by our course of life our hopes of blisse or not, then curiously looke it in the first decree. Our sinnes and miseries require the goodnesse of a mediatour: as for a Sophister to dispute the occasion we need not; especially since, as <hi>Arminius</hi> himselfe concludeth, these points be not requisite neither to be <hi>knowne or beleeued:</hi> it is in his <hi>declaratione sententiae,</hi> before the States.</p>
            <p>Yet are they still so fraught with subtilties, that the very pervsall may seeme of greater danger, then it can be of profit. How often see wee many here to suffer shipwrack, whilst they couet to goe farther then their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26776:9"/> ability or strength will permit them? The Prophet <hi>David</hi> Psal. 36. compareth the iudgements of God to a depth, or an <hi>abysse.</hi> Now in a depth as long as we can finde footing, we be well and safe: but if that faile, a feare streight seizeth on vs of being plunged: thus in abstruser mysteries, as long as we can haue the help of reason too, wee may wade the more securely on:<note place="margin">Et de Orpheo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etiam Hygin Poet. &amp; Astro. nom. L. 2.</note> but when that once is swallowed vp, a mazelesse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion must needs followe. You knowe what Poets faine of <hi>penthem;</hi> he was torne but for viewing too neerely the rites of <hi>Bacchus:</hi> vpon which one of them</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</l>
               <note place="margin">Euripid.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Such wisdome is madnesse outright; You may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how the Lord long since gaue vp the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Philosophers to vanish in their owne deuises, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they vsed the talent of their wits to idle disqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and not to the donours praise; Let vs take heed least we deserue alike sentence, by trespassing too far vpon <hi>Grace,</hi> as they did vpon the light of <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither doe I by this approue the lazie dulnesse of any: not of such who thinke it acutenesse sufficient to cry downe more acute disputes. Men may deseruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly canvase these points, if they shall in their discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, be guided by reason, and not by fancy or bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. It is here as it was in <hi>Ovid</hi> his Medea; a match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse Poem (saith the Rhetoritian) <hi>si ingonio suo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perare</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quintil.</note>
               <hi>maluisset, quàm indulgere,</hi> if he had not beene too lauishly witty. We be placed by nature in a mid distance betweene beasts and Angels: thus also ought our knowledge to bee, lesse then that of Angels, as more then what beasts haue: wee must bee content to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26776:9"/> forgoe many difficulties, of wee can percance vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand any. But so it is, that thos<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who meddle here, do for the most part exceed their limits; as it happeneth in ambition of state, they neuer deeme themselues high enough, till they touch vpon danger. God in many places of Scripture is said to be <hi>a fire,</hi> as Deut. 4. v. 24. Ezek. 8. 2. If to a fire wee approach not too nigh, it comforteth, but otherwise it burnes and scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: so here concerning diuine matters, a temperate knowledge instructeth vs; but a superfluous or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous search confounds the iudgement.</p>
            <p>I will close vp this point with that of <hi>Salvian. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 3.</note>
               <hi>quasi sacrilegae temeritatis est, vt plus seire cupias, quam sinaris:</hi> it is not so much curiosity, as a kinde of sacriledge, to prie into the forbidden secrets of Gods owne closet: it argues a soule presumption in vs of our strength, when as (God knoweth) our knowledge is but small and <hi>weake,</hi> which is my third point.</p>
            <p>Knowledge indeed is the very light of the soule, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a iewell inestimable: yet so apt are men to bee misled by arrogancy, that they inuert that to their harme, which the Lord hath bestowed on them for their greate vse; I told you before of the danger of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching wisdome: of drawing too nigh vnto the <hi>flaming bush,</hi> to which notwithstanding <hi>Moses</hi> might not. Now of this there is no greater an incentiue cause, then this of pride; when men doe fauour more their own wit, then the iustnesse of the argument they haue in hand; for this reason you may note how er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in times past brake forth most rife in the <hi>Eastern</hi> Churches; there that of the Novatians, Eunomians,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26776:10"/> first tooke root, and indeed what not? Whereas these of the <hi>West,</hi> as being placed vnder a duller clime, so were they for heresies losse disposed. The Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (saith <hi>Iraneus</hi>) were men <hi>qui semetitsos perfectos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 2.</note>
               <hi>&amp; vniversorum agnitionem habere dicebant:</hi> they deem'd themselues as it were composed of wit and knowledge; neither is it a rare sight to see men now adaies to slip from pride to errour: whilst not being seasoned with charity, they swell with selfe conceipt. Hence the Apostle layeth it for a principall and main ground of <hi>perverse doctrines,</hi> 1. Tim. 6.</p>
            <p>But alas, what is the highest pitch of mans science? or wherein doth he so excell, but in that he may bee said best to know, if he confesse his ignorance; Can he sound the true depth of the least point in nature? is be able to satisfie himselfe in any triuiall obiect? Looke but vpon the loadstone, and thou shalt find as many amazing wonders, as there be properties. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the <hi>remora</hi> so called: shew mee how so small a creature doth check the tallest ship in its full course: view the curious frame of mans body: ponder the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of the buried seed, <hi>Vbi{que}</hi> (saith <hi>Scaliger) cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exercit.</note>
               <hi>est nos nihil scire:</hi> one neuerthelesse, who did (I beleeue) iudge as charitably of himselfe, as another men. Reason and sense be the only or chiefe promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our knowledge in this world; now these for the most part, are as subiect to errour, as weak in their helpes, whereby it hapneth that those things which we doe vnderstand, we know but in the tine &amp; slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: like <hi>Aesop's</hi> Fox, who did licke the outside of the glasse, when he could not come at the substance.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:26776:10"/>
            <p>As for tumor then and height of conceipt, it argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing here, but want of an experienced insight: the very claime to much knowledge proues this, that the title is neither good nor right; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes it a principle, that such pretenders, at least wise concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Christian doctrine, were but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> meere nouices 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. In the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Ch. he couples them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>proud and knowing nothing</hi> v. 4. vpon the<note place="margin">Festu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum singnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione; Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius &amp; Naeuius in fragmentis</note> same ground perhaps also the word <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>frunitus</hi> of the ancient latines, doth as well imply an insolem man, as one that is void of sence; when the limbs swell and wax ouer big, it is no signe of health in the body, but rather of a dropsie, or some disease: so tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this arrogancy proceedeth most commonly from an vnsoundnes of the braine, as not comprehending yet but what the vastnesse of knowledge is.</p>
            <p>Hence, those bitings and censures against others: such malignant vndervalewing, whereby wee lessen our brothers name that wee may encrease our owne; <hi>livor</hi> (saith <hi>Petrarch) Semper lippus est:</hi> this humor alwaies is ill sighted: it discerneth not of worth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but of that only which is nigh at hand, nay in the possessour: Although so ill a custome doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing augment their repute who practise it. The moone may darken and eclips the sunne, but withall it looseth its owne light: and they by deprauing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers worth, make their owne to be suspected.</p>
            <p>But now on the other side, men of growth and good proceedings in knowledge bee nothing so; <hi>Moses</hi> it is recorded, was a man skilled in all the <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>Aegyptians:</hi> yet afterwards wee finde,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26776:11"/> that he was not more learned then meeke &amp; modest, <hi>The meekest man vpon earth Numb. 12. v.</hi> 3. In truth such doe well conceiue the length and breadth of sciences, as not to be waded thorough; they are so far from nourishing a great opinion within themselues, that they labour also to beate it downe elswhere; <hi>non</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. ad marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin.</note>
               <hi>placet cùm <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>charissimis, &amp;c.</hi> It is not pleasing to mee (saith S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Austin</hi>) that my friends doe so ouerprize my worth: It is understood by them, how the knowledge of this point doth but lead vs into the ignorance of another; how the infinitnesse of learning groweth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs in the very getting of it. If men walke abroad the heauens stem at euery small distance to close with the earth: but whē they approach thether, as large a space opens forthwith as they haue left behinde; thus in the course of learning; vpon any purchase of some little insight we hope anon to rest accomplisht; but when we ariue there farther difficulties arise before vs; still there remaineth something behinde vnscand; <hi>For as yet we know but in part 1. Cor.</hi> 13. vpon which some haue made this obseruation, that in this life wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a greater likenesse with God through the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouement of our wils, then by that of the reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faculty; Holy wee may bee in a bigger measure, then we can be wise and learned.</p>
            <p>But suppose thou hast attained to the highest top of all science: that thou vndestandest as much as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels doe, <hi>what hast thou, that thou didst not receiue, and if thou didst receiue it, why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not receiued it?</hi> Men doe not vsually boast of those things which doe outwardly accrew vnto
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26776:11"/> them; thence he in the tragedian scoffingly,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui genus iactat suum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aliena laudat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> it must be something of their owne industry and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuement that pufs them vp: now knowledge, it is chiefly a gift of Gods benevolence: hee giueth to one the power of tongues: to another the vnderstanding of artes; and to all as best him pleaseth.</p>
            <p>I speake not of an infused science; not of the ability which the Prophets and Apostles had: but that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise of the common straine may seeme in a peculiar manner to proceed from God; Neither yet know I, how far forth here he affordeth his influence, by what concurse: onely I am perswaded that he doth concur vnto this by a more speciall aide, then to other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues<note place="margin">Vid ad initia. 7. L. de artibus.</note> of the like ranke; Euen the Philosophers concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing this, had there deities (as <hi>Capella</hi> also alludeth) to whom seuerally they did attribute each art; who, if hee doth consider those prime fathers of the Church: how powerfully they withstood troopes of heresies out of the copiousnesse of their knowledge: who can imagine but that they were thus helpt? Yet not by inspiration, but by a particular and vnknowne assistance; <hi>Euery good gift, &amp; euery perfect gift is from aboue. Ia.</hi> 1. 17. and for this the <hi>Philosopher</hi> in his Ethicks maketh his felicity or chiefe good <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a gift of God; Now there is no endowment of the minde more excellent then this of knowledge; it is the eye and guide of the rest, if wee doe not abuse it through selfe-conceipt: if, as ventmous beasts wont to doe by nutriture, we turne not that to poyson and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26776:12"/> our hurt, which of it selfe is good.</p>
            <p>I will end this point with the words of the Apostle: <hi>If any man thinke that hee knoweth any thing, hee knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know:</hi> he knoweth not according to sobriety: not according to the rule of holy <hi>writ</hi> and <hi>reuealed</hi> grace, which is my last point.</p>
            <p>Since mans speculations and fancies of themselues are so extrauagant, God hath wisely prouided lawes to binde them withall. Now lawes (saith the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi>) bee either <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> writs &amp; promulged, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> namely <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rcible customes, but no where inrowled:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and so is the rule wherewith God guideth our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in divine mysteries, partly described in his word, and sometimes reuealed besides the holy writ.</p>
            <p>As for the word it is a treasury full of most rare knowledge. There are who hold no art or science to be extant, which is not at least wise implicitly contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it: for, say they, some clauses doe here appeare of each faculty: some prints and footsteps. On this manner haue <hi>Criticks</hi> likewise thought all Philosophy to ly hid in <hi>Homer,</hi> and iudge him as various an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist, as an excellent Poet. Either opinion I let passe, though not as vnprobable, yet as remote from my purpose; Certaine it is that whatsoe're may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily beget, or encrease a divine knowledge, the Lord hath amply set downe in his word; For he hath not giuen it along to conforme our wils, but also to enrich the tables of our vnderstanding; <hi>to make vs wise 2 Tim.</hi> 3. It is confest to be a kinde of science, as farre surpassing the rest in worth, as divinity doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26776:12"/> fraile nature. Dauid though a prophet protest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that hee grew thereby more <hi>wise,</hi> then were his teachers: How often doth he pray and entreat to bee fully instructed in it.</p>
            <p>So then, that conceipt of the Cardinall <hi>L. 4. De verbo Dei,</hi> is but a meere figment; as if things of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon need, were comprized therein, and not matters of peculiar &amp; secret vse. It is said to be as a <hi>light that shineth in a darke place 2. Pet. 1. a Candle p<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t on a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle stick Mat.</hi> 5. 15. Now a light so placed, doth not lighten only the open rooome, but every nooke and comer thereof. Nay I will adde, it is an <hi>armory</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing the zealous dispurer with proofes against so blasphemous tenents; a <hi>garden</hi> out of which the holy dispenser may decke vp his discourse into a Prophets phrase; what things are of necessary and a f<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing vse be there most plainly disclosed; others indeed but dimly; whereas the word growes obscure, so should our search bee more cautelous and circumspect; wee must not vent our coniectures for oracles at all, least whilst we annex such glosses, we corrupt the text. The good <hi>Samaritan</hi> in the 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>Luke</hi> deliuered <hi>two</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 6. Et Ambrosius in exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one advirgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. L.</note>
               <hi>pence</hi> to the host for the wounded traueller: <hi>two pence</hi> (saith <hi>Optatus</hi>) that is Christ hath bequeathed vnto vs for our soules health both lawes, the old and the new; He promiseth there that what should be laid out more, if not lauifhly perchance, or idely, he would see it discharged: so may wee for out sober disputes, either vpon or besides the word expect a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence; but if they appeare superfluous or repugnant, they be no longer descants, but sinfull devises.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:26776:13"/>
            <p>Humane inuentions then come short of a diuine authority: they may serue vs for illustrations, but not for a ground and rule: vpon the <hi>word</hi> as touching that efficacy which they haue, must they be builded also; either <hi>expresse,</hi> as there apparent, or at least, <hi>eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiuè,</hi> as being thence fairely and handsomly dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. If wee containe within this compasse wee shall bee as wise as safe: but if wee fly out and follow our fancies, it remaineth that we straight vanish in them. For euen thus did that lewd rable of the <hi>Gnostici:</hi> they<note place="margin">L. 2. c. 46. 47. &amp;c.</note> set the scriptures aside (saith <hi>Iraeneus</hi>) betaking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues to their proper coniectures: The <hi>Psalmist</hi> oft'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time likneth the word of God vnto a path or <hi>way:</hi> nay it is <hi>via Regia,</hi> as one styleth it: the <hi>high way</hi> to blisse: now most commonly vpon each side of such waies there bee ditches and miery bogs: so here on either hand the wordly heresies and numberles er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, dangerous to bee slipt into; it is best then to keepe the beaten and trodden way, the word.</p>
            <p>But againe; sometimes the Lord speaketh as well by <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> as hee doth in the written word: for he hath not tied himselfe so strictly vnto the word, but that hee can, if he please, vary the manner of his communication with his beloued Saints. Our <hi>Fathers</hi> in the first nonage of the Church, well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood the benefit of this; a dreame or vision to them did as easily cleere each doubt, as either their owne weaknesse, or the occurrency of businesse could sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest it. But to auouch the truth, now in these later dayes, such extraordinary meanes of grace bee well nigh out of late; Prophecy, &amp; reuelation, &amp; tongues,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26776:13"/> with other gifts, we finde conioyn'd 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Since as there appeareth no miracle of tongues or prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, neither is it to be beleeued that revelations are very frequent; Hauing <hi>Moses</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> wee may not expect new messages from the dead, nor yet from aboue; <hi>Calvin</hi> is confident to vpbraid Such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Enthusiasts</hi> with downe right madnesse: <hi>minus errore agitantur, quam rabie;</hi> they be not (saith hee) so much mistaken as quite distracted; when as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I make reuelation a rule of our wisdome, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in it selfe, but not so vsually if we respect the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent age; it is if it were, but this no way causeth it to be: Our best <hi>Enthusiasmes</hi> now must bee our prayers and diligence in the sacred word.</p>
            <p>Trie then at least wee must <hi>the spirits</hi> as S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> warneth vs, least a dreame or idle conceipt delude vs<note place="margin">2. Sam. 10. Vincentius contra Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses c. 24. &amp; Rhenanus in Annotationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> with the esteeme of a classicke reuelation; least as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> did once in counselling <hi>Dauid,</hi> such Prophets speake without the <hi>Ephod;</hi> for what draue <hi>Tertullian</hi> more effectually vpon <hi>Montanisme?</hi> And if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vse the good father Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> as for <hi>Visions</hi> hee may seeme to credit them ouermuch; so apt are men to rely on the slights of fancy, raising miracles out of the braine, when those of the hands be ceased; yea in former times this liberty of imagination grew so far, as into a sect of Hereticks, termed the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; who could as they thought by helpe of diuine illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, expound the <hi>Scriptures</hi> vpon first sight. As <hi>Samuel</hi> then being called by God himselfe, once or twice mistooke the sound for old <hi>Elies</hi> voice <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 3. so must we be carefull that contrariwise we entertaine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26776:14"/> not some crotchet of mans braine for a diuine <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithstanding all this, if hauing examined such inspirations by the touch of sacred <hi>writ,</hi> wee finde them accordingly; a <hi>rule</hi> they may be; yet here againe you must note, what reuelations I meane; not new &amp; vnheard of <hi>respectu doctrina reuelatae,</hi> as the <hi>Papists</hi> would, lessening thereby the sufficiency of the word: but new <hi>respectu actus reuelandi:</hi> such onely as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers in matters of fact, not encrease the Canon of our faith: such alone may be the guide of the <hi>wisdome</hi> here discussed.</p>
            <p>The summe of all that hath beene spoken hitherto is this. It is to be wished that we had no occasion to deale upon such deepe <hi>mysteries</hi> at all; since our life is fraile, and our ayme eternall blisse, it were expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that we endeauoured more to become pious, then subtill and acute; <hi>Epictetus</hi> the <hi>Stoicke</hi> could once complaine of his time; whereas (saith he) there be two parts of <hi>Philosophy:</hi> the first and more especiall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a practise of wholsome precepts well digested: the second <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatiue and curious disquiry; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we haue quite inuerted the course. How many now a daies frame their diuiner studies after this method? How doe they chiefly intend sublimer, though fruitlesse controversies; yea and moreouer, which is as bad, oft times those here vndertake these points, whose shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for such a burden be most vnfit. <hi>Fight ye not with small or great saue onely with the king af Israel,</hi> was the charge of the <hi>Syrian</hi> king to the Captaines of his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26776:14"/> host, 2. Chron. 18. Even so there be who as soone as they can but spell in diuinity, fasten alone vpon the greatest difficulties; whereby it commeth to passe, that they cleere not the doubts which they take in hand, but rather betray their owne weaknesse.</p>
            <p>Or secondly, since by reason of our insulting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries on either side, some must needs looke into these points, it is meete that wee dispole our selues with a graue consideration of this afore hand; <hi>Daniel</hi> before he receaued those strange visions, fasted three whole weekes, Dan. 10. 3. And <hi>Iamblychus</hi> the <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorean</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. de. myst<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e rijs Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum.</note> relateth how the <hi>Aegyptian Priests</hi> went to prepare themselues for their supposed <hi>Enthusiasmes</hi> with musicke and abstinence; I vrge not this for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample sake, but only to shew with what <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euerence we should addresse our selues to so diuine a taske: not rudely setting vpon it, but with mature aduice: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides in the enterprize it selfe, let vs vse great sobriety, avoiding that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2. Tim. 2. or nice acutenesse; a fault vnseemly each where, as well in religion, as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arts: for which <hi>Minerva</hi> is feigned to hate the Spider, because she spinneth too curious a web. In a word let vs evermore submit fancie to reason, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to faith, both to Gods word, or his especiall reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. These two be that helping <hi>glasse</hi> of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge here, or double <hi>spectacle,</hi> of which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> speaketh. <hi>Now wee see through a glasse darkely, but then face to face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I haue, though weakly, made vp a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course concerning <hi>Divine Mysteries,</hi> and our <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of them. A <hi>Text</hi> in my indgement, as befitting
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26776:15"/> this auditory, as my selfe, for this my first assay. Wee sit all here by the well-spring of <hi>Wisdome</hi> and science, &amp; most of vs may hereafter serue at the altar in Gods owne house. It is not amisse that we know our limits, as also consider our strengths. Vnder the old law the <hi>Levite</hi> might goe farther into the Temple, then the <hi>Lay,</hi> and a <hi>Priest</hi> then the <hi>Levite:</hi> so in these points concerning the <hi>mysticall</hi> temple, Apoc. 21. 22. One may wade farther then another: but as there none could enter into the chiefest sanctuary, saue onely the high <hi>Priest:</hi> so neither here hath any full accesse, into the secrets of these <hi>mysteries,</hi> but only our high <hi>Priest</hi> and Saviour Christ: <hi>In whom are hid all the treasures of wisdome and knowledge,</hi> Colos. 2. 3. As for vs as long as we abide in this life, we must be satisfied with a meaner knowledge of such things: with certaine glympses at most: like benighted travailers, who if the moone hap to be ouerclouded, are content with star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. Now to the only <hi>wise</hi> God, who is able to doe aboue that which we can either speake or imagine, be ascribed all glory, power, praise, and dominion this day and foreuer. <hi>Amen</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26776:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TOVCHING</hi> CHVRCH-SCHISMES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ROM. 16. VER. 17.</bibl>
                  <p>Brethren marke them which cause divisions and offences, contrary to the doctrine, which yee haue learned and avoid them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Carcely had our Apostle here laid the grounds of <hi>Christian</hi> religion, but it presently meetes on each side with strong opposers. The Diuell was straight wayes ready to excite errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and factious spirits against the truth. What <hi>Poets</hi> faigne of hate and contentions beside their <hi>Iupiter's</hi> palace, is really true of the house of God.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <note place="margin">Hesiode.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Eager debates closely still as 'twere environ the Church. Alwaies there bee who like the <hi>Dragon,</hi> Apoc. 12. 4. are ready to devoure it euen in its birth. Neither yet doth this so inbred enmity betwixt the patrons of truth and errour, happen without God's especiall allowance.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:26776:16"/>
            <p>For, first hereby hee sifts and winnowes all alike. As many as settle firmely together he takes for solid graine: but those who are carried away with each blast of new doctrine, for fruitlesse <hi>chasse.</hi> They neuer were sincerely orthodox, but either temporizing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malists, or at most coldly devoted.</p>
            <p>Againe by this he keepes his elect from rust and an over secure ease: out of loue hee permits them not to slumber in such a tranquility as might at length pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce some hurtfull effect. <hi>Calamitas</hi> (saith he in <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius) virtutum disciplina est:</hi> Crosses and all kinds of opposition, doe not so much afflict Gods Saints, as truely exercise them.</p>
            <p>Thus doth the Lord effect the good of his chosen by the hands of malignant <hi>Schismaticks.</hi> But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding though he deale so in prouidence, yet their offence and guilt is nothing thereby abated. For in the third to the Philipp, the Apostle plainely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth such to be <hi>evill workers, very dogges.</hi> v. 3. In the 18<seg rend="sup">th</seg> v. he termes them enimies of the crosse of Christ, <hi>whose end is destruction,</hi> v. 19. and here in my Text, he iudgeth them vnworthy euen of the solace and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of humane commerce. <hi>Brethren marke them which &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Text, like to those <hi>shafts</hi> of the holy candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticke,<note place="margin">Division.</note> vpon euery word beares knops of flowers: please you then to take notice of: First, the thing here spoken against, namely <hi>divisions</hi> and <hi>offences</hi> in the Church. Secondly, their more especiall property which is to be <hi>contrary to some doctrine afore learned.</hi> Thirdly the persons or those, who <hi>cause</hi> them. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26776:16"/> the manner how such disturbers must be delt with, First <hi>marke,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>avoid</hi> them. Lastly, on the other side, the entire and mutuall agreement among true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, or as it is here their <hi>brotherhood.</hi> Of these or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly in that method I haue proposed, and first con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>divisions</hi> and <hi>offences</hi> themselues.</p>
            <p>There is nothing which doth more preserue the<note place="margin">P. 1.</note> world in being then <hi>vnity</hi> and agreement. It is the stay and bond of every thing; by how much the nee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer they participate of this, by so much the more they enioy a certaine existence. <hi>Zoroaster</hi> as implying God that first and chiefest vnity termes it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the matrix or fountaine within which all things be originally concluded; Except in nature the heauens did embrace this globe below: vnlesse here the elements did combine thus louingly as they doe, so stately a fabricke could not long subsist; it must needs loose its being, because it should loose its har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. In matter of policy consent of minds legally disposed makes a state: without this it remaines no longer a state, but a rude and vngoverned desart. To speake in the phrase of moderne Philosophy, mutuall concord is, <hi>forma totalis;</hi> that which wholy giues a body politicke both life and beauty; But aboue all in the house or Church of God seemes this vnitie of greatest value. <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptisme,</hi> wee finde commended, Ephes. 4. 5. As in the structure of the old tabernacle, by loopes &amp; taches were the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines aptly conioyned: so in the antitype, namely the Church, doth this spirit of <hi>Vnity</hi> diffusing it selfe throughout the parts, knit them vp into an entire frame.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:26776:17"/>
            <p>This being so; sithence each where a concord is so requisite, but most in the Church, how fowly doe they trespasse that breake this bond? with what sharpnesse deserue they to be handled who breed diuisions? The Fathers amidst their writings doe presse no one point more frequently or eagerly then this; Every where they take occasion, after S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> manner, as well to condemne all rents and <hi>Schismes,</hi> as extoll a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an like accord. <hi>Optatus</hi> in a word makes such diuisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Summum malorum,</hi> a crime so beinous, as that none can match it. And indeed if you rightly weigh the examples of Gods wrath and punishments, you will not much mislike his iudgment. In the 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of Gen. when <hi>Cain</hi> had slaine his brother, God onely markes him and lets him goe: nay hee is iealous least any might <hi>kill Cain,</hi> v. 15. To that great and sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous city of <hi>Ninive</hi> what doth he? Only <hi>Ionas</hi> is sent to teach and warne them. Insteed of ruine comes a gentle embassage. But for <hi>Corath</hi> and his complices, those mutiners in the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> behold a suddaine destruction: the earth openeth and entombes them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue; whence it followes not without some shew of probability, that <hi>Church-Schismes</hi> more displease the Lord, then either murther or sacrilege. <hi>Austin</hi> yet goes farther; for in his 50<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Ep. discoursing about the obstinacy of the factious Donatists, he chargeth them with no lesse a sinne, then with that of the holy ghost.</p>
            <p>But the heinousnesse of <hi>divisions</hi> will better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if we examine them, First in their <hi>obiect.</hi> It is no slight or vulgar argument; perchance in the disqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of such points, dissent may afford greater profit,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26776:17"/> namely by exercising the wit, then a present accord. But it is religion, that prop of mans conscience, and path to blisse. Vpon this narrow way doe men lye daily striuing and iustly in opinions, not without much hindrance in their intended iourney. Religion indeed of it selfe is rather a ground of common agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Religio</hi> thinke some a <hi>religando</hi> from binding the hearts of the professors, as well in a mutuall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as in obedience to God: yet if happily it bee made the subiect of strifes and debates, they no where<note place="margin">L. 2. 2.</note> burne more fiercely, <hi>nulla infest a hominibus bestia,</hi> (could <hi>Ammian<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Marcellin<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> an heathen say) <hi>vt sunt sibi ferales pleri{que} Christiani.</hi> No beasts are so vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, as Christians be, when once they iarre in points of doctrine. The reason may bee; men for the most part hug their peculiar <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ents with a too ouerprizing loue. And as they doe thus in all other arts, so espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in matters of Christianity &amp; faith. Having then fancied some opinion here as greatly appertaining to the foules health, they must necessarily abhorte those who so ere oppose it.</p>
            <p>Next in a second place consider the vsuall and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diffusion of <hi>Schismes.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> compares them<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> to a <hi>Canker:</hi> now a canker resteth not, but eats for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward till the member bee consumed: on this manner doe false and erroneous doctrines: being once broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched they creepe from man to man, vntill they haue corrupted the Church throughout. Of this our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Apostle had a feeling experiment: for as one forsaken, 2. Tim. 1. hee complaineth that all in Asia were turn'd aside. So naturally apt are men to admit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26776:18"/> of a fancy nere so vnprobable, if once on foot. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so only: falshood too alwaies is more fertile then truth: it straightway multiplies into seuerall and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse streames beyond the head. Those manifold blasphemies wherewith the primitiue Church was pestered, what were they saue so many branches of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his doctrine that first hereticke. <hi>Arrius</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 2.</note> indeed (saith <hi>Russinus</hi>) vented one single heresie tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the natiuity of our Saviour: but ere long this one becomes a triple monster. As then, Lev. 13. v. 8. if the plague in a mans flesh spread, not otherwise, the Priest pronounced him leaprous and vncleane: so here, there is no plea against <hi>Schismes</hi> more aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their foulnesse, then because thus strangely they both spread and multiply.</p>
            <p>Lastly consider their irksome and long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: how they persist not for a day or yeare, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly for length of ages. It were some happinesse if as easily as they burst forth and ouerflow, they could as quickly bee stopped. Those <hi>tares,</hi> Mat. 13. v. 24. sprang vp on a sudden: but as for the extirpation and rooting them vp, wee finde it deferred till the great haruest. Errors in truth are by nature <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, very obstinate; what once is vented falsely, is here maintain'd, if but for credits sake. As much as wants in strength and cleerenesse of argument, they supply with a colour of perseuerance; giue them leaue to take but root, they will flourish of themselues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either watring or attendance: so that as <hi>Sulla</hi> spake of warres, <hi>sumi facile, caterum acerrimè desine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> the same is true of refractory Schismes. Any man
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26776:18"/> neuer so meane, may sow a fond opinion: but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse and curbe it seemes a taske of the highest skill.</p>
            <p>You haue heard briefly concerning <hi>diuisions</hi> in grosse; how execrable they bee whether you attend their <hi>obiect</hi> or boundlesse <hi>diffusion;</hi> but chiefly for their long and obstinat <hi>continuance:</hi> cleauing almost as lastingly to the Church, as the leprosie did to the house of <hi>Gehazai;</hi> This is there condition, this their nature: It followeth methodically in my 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg> point, that I handle their especiall property, which is to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to some <hi>doctrine afore learned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery art and faculty hath some maine ground to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> rely vpon: Some chiefe axiomes by which it is guided in its inferiour positions no otherwise then by a card or polestar. These axiomes ought alwaies to be sure and firmely establisht; for if they also bee exposed to doubtfull enquiries, the whole science straight begins to shake. In this respect as the <hi>Grammarian</hi> prettily descants, the alphabet in all languages stands <hi>indecli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,</hi> because it's the foundation of that first art-Christian religion although no perfect science, yet likewise it supposeth certaine principles: a few grounds and rules vpon which the minde may rest. Now as wee speake in Philosophy of a double mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; there is <hi>mensura actiua,</hi> that which is so primarily and in it selfe; againe, there is <hi>mensura passiua;</hi> such a one as being measured before, measures something else: so in case of religion, you may discerne of a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold rule; one principall, namely the holy writ: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with reference vnto this, to wit the constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Cannons of the Church. Against these two
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26776:19"/> doe the authors of <hi>heresies</hi> and <hi>schismes,</hi> particularly aime their forces.</p>
            <p>First the <hi>Heretique,</hi> as subornde with a bolder ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, is wont more directly to oppose the very text. In former times we finde them so impudent as that they durst change and mangle it as seemde them best; witnesse the <hi>Cerinthians, Marcionists,</hi> with the rest of that franticke crew; not enduring so pure a light should shine vpon their monstrous blasphemies, they either wrongfully concealed it vnder a <hi>bushell,</hi> or quite renounc't it; Indeed the <hi>Papists</hi> now a more refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ofspring, deale with greater caution; yet in effect they performe as much, whilst they groundlesly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the sacred Canon, or else countenance against it their idle <hi>traditions;</hi> for by adding superfluously vnto the old, what doe they lesse then create a new word;</p>
            <p>Thus doe <hi>Heretiques</hi> some way still infringe the text: But now for <hi>Schismaticks</hi> they meddle in those points which fall more preoperly within the Churches verge; And here they vary and swarue from the right on either hand; vpon one stand such as conspiring with vs in doctrinall grounds, differ onely touching the outward surface: As children who otherwise mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually well disposed, yet wrangle about their nuts &amp;<note place="margin">Leo. Austi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e contra de Laxu Arri<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram sabbatario Sidon Appoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>is L. 1.</note> toyes. Concerning these externall <hi>rites</hi> what tumults haue beene raised? How frowardly doe men still stand forth against the <hi>Church</hi> in termes point blanke? Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting almost with the <hi>Manichees</hi> of old vpon such daies, as that keepes feast; Not a bare <hi>diuision</hi> hath serued here, vnlesse a locall secession were made; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26776:19"/> at lestwise by some peculiar notes of sanctity, they as yet remaine distinguisht: like to those seeming <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers</hi> among the heathen, who had their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iulian Ep. Lucian</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, some odd habit or other, to exempt them from the rout; But I leaue this soare as too too hardned for a plaister. A rent so great in our Israel, that well nigh ten tribes, I feare me, be this way fallen off.</p>
            <p>Those more neerely concerne my drift, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne some reall points of doctrine. Now some doe this expresly and without a glosse. Before <hi>Arminius</hi> let loose his tenents, he first questions openly the <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke</hi> Catechisme: <hi>Consentaneum rationi, &amp;c.</hi> it is meet (saith he) and very expedient that such <hi>Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> be newly renewed. As long as they stood fast and plausible, well he knew his acuter doctrine could hardly gaine entrance; But as the Lord commands touching land-markes Deut. 10. v. 24. not to remoue them, because they haue there beene anciently ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: so in Church affaires 'tis best that old and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticke <hi>decisions</hi> doe still prevaile; Are wee wiser then our Fathers? Or is our vnderstanding beyond the ancients? If in a common weale as the <hi>Philosopher</hi> noteth, former lawes should not hastily giue place to new; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: least by often changing their respect be somewhat impaired; much<note place="margin">Pol. 2.</note> lesse in positions of a <hi>Christian</hi> beliefe. It causeth the mindes of men to wauer much: it begets scruples and <hi>offences,</hi> which our Apolstle also here condemneth.</p>
            <p>Others at least in shew approue the receiued <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> but no otherwise then for their own advantage;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26776:20"/> vnder pretext of those generall rules they vent some priuate and moderne conceipts. It was a diuise (saith <hi>Seneca</hi>) concerning his times of many lewd and rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous liuers, to cloake their luxury by pretending to the Epicurean sect. Thus they shrowd their wrong and false opinions in the <hi>Churches</hi> bosome; not deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a meaning from thence, but fastning there one vpon it; how much better were it, if they left the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> free and still vnbounded. For by thus drawing them downe into a more particular sense, they haue troubled the Church with needlesse disquiries; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> the geeat speaking vnto the <hi>Nicene</hi> counsell,<note place="margin">Gelasi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> is bold to call those disputes betweene <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: a vaine and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse debate: Rather then the catholique peace should suffer disturbance, hee disliketh an exact discussion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a point of faith. I dare not prescribe vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally an implicit beliefe, not such an one as seales vp the vnderstanding, whilst it kindles a blinde zeale: yet happily in doubts which grow besides the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it may well suffice. The woman diseased of a bloody <hi>flux</hi> Mark. 5. v. 25. couets onely to touch Christs <hi>garment:</hi> shee stands not vpon circumstances how or whence an healing vertue should flow: neither need wee perchance to dig so particularly into those positions, which our forefathers haue left vndetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. At once it costs more anxiety, then it can afford either content or gaine.</p>
            <p>Well then: let both principles of <hi>Church tenents</hi> &amp; <hi>Scripture</hi> stand in force; as <hi>Aarons</hi> rod eat vp those wherewith the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> contended, they will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26776:20"/> discountenance &amp; cōsume any vpstart issue of fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; for by the way you may note: errors and truth doe not spring vp alike; this leasurely and with a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring encrease: that hastily like the sunne in his we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne course, which cuts most nimbly about the line: but as there the sunne proceeds but slowly in degrees farther distant: so here doe errors after their first bruit and flourish: if the ancient grounds be still vpheld: if we retaine this defence to withstand their onset.</p>
            <p>I haue shewed you the maine property of <hi>Schismes;</hi> a dangerous quality, you see, in a Christian estate; for as <hi>Sampson</hi> did to ouerwhelme the Philistins Iud. 18. 29. it puls away both <hi>Pillars</hi> wherevpon the Church is sounded. Now afterwards you haue thus had their property, it remaines that in my third point I decypher their subiect, to wit the persons or those which <hi>cause</hi> them.</p>
            <p>It is true that as the Lord hath planted a vineyard; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> so hath he hedged and fenct' it round. But what can possibly keepe out malitious <hi>Schismaticks?</hi> Euer and anon they breake through this fence, dispoyling mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serably so precious a ground plot. And this they doe, either from an inward corruption of nature, or else induced by some externall motiues: concerning their nature, you may note them to haue beene men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly of a fierce &amp; abrupt temper; S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Paul</hi> I am sure describes them so 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. Of this humour as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> witnesseth, was <hi>Hermogenes</hi> of old, <hi>naturâ turbulentus,</hi> a fit materiall to frame an hereticke; Not vnlike vnto him wee finde <hi>Novatus</hi> in <hi>Cyprian;</hi> one who more esteemed his owne will and fancy; then the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26776:21"/> quiet of the Church: such men goe on in a violent course: wheresoere they appeare, raising some storme or tempest: they carry indeed fire in their <hi>Censors,</hi> yet not to sacrifice, but to kindle publicke debates. Farre better doth S. <hi>Iames</hi> instruct such with <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>meeknesse</hi> of <hi>wisdom. Iam.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
            <p>Neither yet as I said want they outward fewell to encrease, this inbred aptnesse. First here occurs an<note place="margin">Varr<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> hope of honour &amp; advancement; This as one speakes of beauty hath <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: it distorts and drawes the sight besides the truth; when <hi>Alcimus 1 Mat.</hi> 7. affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the <hi>high priesthood,</hi> hee calls in the <hi>Syrians</hi> to backe his suite, not without extreame hazard of the <hi>Iewish</hi> estate: no otherwise doe they: rather then misse of dignities, they'le endanger the Church with forren tenents; any way shall helpe, before they will sit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled. We reade of <hi>Arrius</hi> as otherwise of a good &amp; honest man; his fault was somewhat too aspiring a minde. It is so with most: they square not their drifts by religion, but religion by their drifts of eminency or profit.</p>
            <p>Secondly by this, as they conceaue, they much enhance their fame. To bee the author or revivour of some nicer <hi>Doctrine</hi> must needs seeme a master peice of no vsuall knowledge; Indeed the Apostle himselfe <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 29. forbares to build the Gospell vpon <hi>grounds</hi> forelaid. This hee did to avoide emergent scandals, but they for by respects: least they bee thought a meere accession of anothers wit or credit. Yet here obserue their grosse mistake; Truth saith the <hi>Philosophers;</hi> likewise vertue is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a thing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26776:21"/> of small and narrow extent; But as for errors, they ly in multitudes and troupes round about; If then in so vast a number of fashoods, they pitch vpon one what glory is it? If missing the center they pricke each part of the circle else? To bolt an errour then is no hard exploit; And as its beginnning is thus prompt and easy, so also is the maintaining of it once begun; Insooth falshood in point of religion commonly someway toucheth vpon the deepest mysteries; it will be sure of a cause pregnāt enough wherein to deale: <hi>Pelagianisme</hi> how doth it in close those large queries concerning gods power and hidden decree? As therefore marriners wont for to say, giue them <hi>winde and Sea roome</hi> they feare no ship wracke: so in such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and boundlesse disputes, it may argue a shallow braine that is quickly graueled; if nere so prest he finde not still scope as well to decline the aduersary, as to reinforce his tenents.</p>
            <p>A last incentiue here may bee an itching desire in men of seeming actiue; rather then rest vnbusied, they will doe some vnnecessary mischiefe. It pleaseth them greatly in their pride of wit to behold those combusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which themselues haue caused. The associates of Catiline in his conspiracy against Rome were the more forward, saith the historian, <hi>vt quiet a mouerent:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salust.</note> that at least they might vnsettle a state so well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed; many endeauour a disturbance of the christian peace for no serious intendment: they raise debates that they may bee said to haue raised them; like hote furious spirits abroad, who delight soly in fights and vproares; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, meere louers of strife.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:26776:22"/>
            <p>Vpon these motiues fore cited doe <hi>Schismaticks</hi> chiefly vndermine the Churches vnity; men other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise oftimes of no meane esteeme and worth. But as it was said of <hi>Curio</hi> the tribune, that he was <hi>facun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dussed malo publico:</hi> euen so they in truth seeme able and sufficiently learned, but it is to the Churches an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance: whilst they imploy those gifts perversly, with which they might haue aduanced the common good.</p>
            <p>Yet also giue me leaue, if a little I misdoubt such: if I iudge them not throughly sound at heart; In 13. <hi>Nehem. v.</hi> 33. where the <hi>Israelitish</hi> parents mix with the women of <hi>Ashdod,</hi> the children speake an vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine idiome: halfe the Ammonitish language; and halfe the Iewish; examine their tracts and discourses aright, they may seeme the issue of a mixt faith. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion if once ambiguous cannot choose but betray it selfe; some sparkles will here breake forth, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so carefully supprest; wherefore as <hi>Iosuah</hi> asked the angell <hi>Ios. 5. v. 13. art thou for vs or for our aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries?</hi> Let me likewise demand; whose part take they? for now by walking so doubtfully and in a mist, they merit applause from neither side; more reason there is that they bee refused of both; Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where speaking touching such neutrals the <hi>Hebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Dum volunt</hi> (saith he) <hi>&amp; Iudaei &amp; Christiani esse, nec sunt Iudaei nec Christiani:</hi> whilst they hang betweene two sects, they deserue to bee ranked no where: meere <hi>batts</hi> in religion are they; as nature hath placed these as twere in no certaine degree ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of beastes or foules: thus they for there ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26776:22"/> profession, may hardly be numbred among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians in any ranck.</p>
            <p>You haue seene the subiect of <hi>divisions</hi> briefly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plai'd; persons very contagious in the Church, and as <hi>Miriam,</hi> long since a <hi>Schismaticke</hi> too, leprous throughout. It is not vnseasonable, if therefore in my fourth point I prescribe the Apostles caution, which is, first <hi>marke,</hi> then <hi>avoid</hi> them.</p>
            <p>What our Saviour forespake touching false tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Math. 7. 15. seemes not more true in regard of their demeanour, then of their preaching &amp; doctrine. They come indeed clothed with <hi>sheepes clothing:</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd ouer with a pretended shew both of truth and zeale. Hard it is in so neere a likelyhood, to discerne where they conforme to the truth, and where they breake off. S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> for this termes them sometimes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, creatures hauing though no more, yet a Christian outside; elsewhere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, exact and able counterfeits. Came they drest in their proper shape, we might the more easily keepe safe; it were no difficult taske to eschew their infectious te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents. A wound if open and apparant, may be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cured; that especially is dangerous, where the soare lies hid, or the passage proues inuolu'd. Well doe <hi>Schismaticks</hi> conceaue the weaknesse of their cause: should they attempt to obtrude their falshhoods vpō the Church, in their naked deformity, it were a vaine designe. Errours be naturally displeasing to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding: whereas truth is no lesse outwardly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, then admirable in it selfe. Therefore they colour &amp; varnish ouer their absurdities with cunning deceipt.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:26776:23"/>
            <p>First, they refute one bad opinion that they may set vp a worse; <hi>Eutiches,</hi> you knowe, would needs<note place="margin">Ep. ad Leon<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> papa<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> maintaine a confusion of natures in Christ; now this he vndertooke (saith <hi>Flavianus</hi>) vnder pretence of confuting <hi>Nestorius,</hi> who held oppositely as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse; Are there none now which cry downe <hi>Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme</hi> whereby to establish <hi>Papisme?</hi> Is there no such new stratagem? Yea farther, are there not those who deale with religion in a sense inverted, as <hi>David</hi> did with king <hi>Ashish,</hi> 1. Sam. 27. vnder shew of fighting against the <hi>Philistins</hi> our adversaries, they fall vpon their countries faith.</p>
            <p>Another way they haue of intermingling truth with errour; Amidst their discourses they craftily mix some drams of verity to commend the rest; nay so they doe more hurt and deeplier infect. Poyson if gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in wine or hony pierceth the veines with greater violence; even thus falshood sweetned with a relish of truth, eats most dangerously into the bowels of the Church.</p>
            <p>A third devise is by faigning of some good intent; whilst they labour a breach in christianity, to make<note place="margin">Orat. de com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponendo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis dissidio inter Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> shew of a desired <hi>vnity</hi> and peace. <hi>Arminius</hi> euen then when hee was forging those opinions vpon which such endlesse troubles haue ensued, compos'de a treatise touching a generall <hi>reconcilement;</hi> like <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>Amasa,</hi> 2. Sam. 20. at once hee offers embraces to the Church and stabe it.</p>
            <p>More shifts besides they skill of to obscure their malitious drifts. There want not infinite tractlesse ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, wherein they can lurke vndiscerned; so as what a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26776:23"/> petty historian speakes of the Ligurians inhabiting bogs and bushy places. <hi>Maior aliquanto labor erat invenire quàm vincere,</hi> may be here applied. It is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier to convince their errours, then perfectly trace it out.</p>
            <p>Not in vaine then are we bid to marke: obserue we ought their subtle passages, mudding still the streame wheresoer'e they goe; neither yet is this enough; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we haue thus descried their falshoods, we must also <hi>avoid</hi> and shun them; <hi>what communion hath light with darknesse</hi> (saith the Apostle) 2. Cor. 6. In the 1. of Gen. v. 4. no sooner had God created <hi>light,</hi> but in the same v. he diuides them straight: wee are though not light, yet the <hi>children</hi> of light, and therefore must be carefull, least by mixing with the sonnes of errour, our light be dim'd and weakned. How seriously dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent were the primitiue Fathers in declining such? How watchfull to represse them? Should I here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count their various <hi>edicts</hi> and <hi>provisoes</hi> framed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, I might happily make more vse of reading, then of moderation and iudgement; Only for a tast; you may from the course of Ecclesiasticall stories gather a treble censure thus disposed. First they inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them <hi>abstension,</hi> or (as I may say) incommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Church: Next a positiue <hi>eiection,</hi> else <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position</hi> from their clericall degree; at length if both these reclaim'd them not, the vtter <hi>Anathema;</hi> Adde here to those seuerer cautions of the Apostolicke Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node, that men rightly orthodox might not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: not ioyne in prayer with such, Can. 44. of the Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, not to deale with them or vse commerce, Can.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26776:24"/> 57. So carefull were those ancient sages, least a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious <hi>Schismaticke,</hi> if let alone, might perchance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the whole Christian flocke.</p>
            <p>It may be in former times there appeared greater danger. About the first plantation of the Gospell, we finde in truth <hi>heresies</hi> more rife and frequent; Satan was then most busie, that he might choak vp the word before it tooke sure root. Thus Mat. 13. 25. the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous one presently sowes his cockle, as soone as the owner had ended. Notwithstanding although such Church diseases be now lesse pregnant, yet are they poysonous still alike. A mixing of things vnwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some with pure, corrupts as much as ere it did.</p>
            <p>Neither doe I (mistake me not) prescribe so ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame a course as the ancients vsed. It is a point both aboue my skill and place: only I wish that alwaies di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbers, of what kinde soeuer, if not in person, yet in doctrine be shunned; that we take heed least by a see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming furtherance of the faith, they hinder its growth. At the fourth of <hi>Ezra</hi> when the people of the land de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to helpe the Israelites in rebuilding the temple, they would not, <hi>Yee haue nothing to doe with vs to build an house,</hi> v. 3. Happily they guessed that for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one stone, they might maliciously plucke downe two. You knowe the fable of the home-bred <hi>wolfe:</hi> vnder colour of keeping the sheepe, hee made more hauock in the fold then the Wolfes abroad. A doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full zeale is most dangerous when thus it gets a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some disguise. It is to bee feared, that such may doe more mischeife, then the adversary from without.</p>
            <p>I haue laid before you at length a full view of Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26776:24"/> their <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>property:</hi> their <hi>subiect</hi> and how they must bee <hi>avoided;</hi> now because one opposite shines more cleerely in anothers presence, it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse that contrariwise in my last point I handle the mutuall agreement of true professours, or as it is here their <hi>Brotherhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read concerning the divisions of <hi>Reuben,</hi> Iudg. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. 15. of much dissention betwixt the <hi>Saduces</hi> and the <hi>Pharises,</hi> Act. 23. 7. Evill and erroneous men are both alike giuen to strife; whereas Christians rightly seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, be no lesse <hi>vnanimous</hi> then abundant in al truth and goodnesse; In the 15<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of Gen. <hi>Abraham</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to take an Heifer, a Ramme, and a Goat: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides a Pigeon with a Turtle: as for the former he <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides</hi>
               <note place="margin">De promissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionibus. <hi>P.</hi> 1<seg rend="sup">ma.</seg>
               </note> them v. 10<seg rend="sup">th</seg>: the Turtle and the Pigeon hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth not. Those three (saith <hi>Prosper</hi>) fore-shew'd the condition of <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> but these the Doue-like and vndiuided agreement of professours truly ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe. Now as the higher faculties of mans soule are two, <hi>will</hi> and the <hi>vnderstanding,</hi> this agreement here consists in a meete consonancy of both.</p>
            <p>First, for the <hi>vnderstanding,</hi> hauing receaued one spirit, they must needs conspire in one meaning and sense: they differ not, as being by the same teacher in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed. Indeed no marvaile if <hi>Schismaticks</hi> doe iarr, whom their own affections or satan diversly instructs: but the Disciples of verity, though many, yet bee they as organs tuned by an individuall spirit. Neither is there a more constant euidence of the truth professed, then such consent; Iudicious interpreters of the sacred writ thence especially inferre, that the Prophets wrot
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26776:25"/> inspir'de; Each where they doe so miraculously con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre,<note place="margin">Vid. B. Vigili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um adversus Euty chem l. 2. lust. Martyr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and fully accord: On the other side dissent of te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, hath euer beene the signe of falshood. The <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to confute the Pagan Philosophers in many principles of faith had no greater proofe: like to a common weale ill composed, they ouerthrew them through their owne discord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, neither yet are orthodox professours thus onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but likewise <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: not alone sympathizing in iudgement, but also in heart; Loue and <hi>vnamity</hi> were euer a most Christian-like note. Looke but into the course of former ages, and you will easily grant as much. Concerning the Apostles time, what ardency of good will finde we there? with what affection did they mutually imbrace? Lands and goods lay then in <hi>common:</hi> the whole Church may seeme no other then one great family. As in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Solomons</hi> temple not any <hi>hammer</hi> or <hi>iron toole</hi> was vsed that made a noise, 1. Reg. 6. Thus they labour'd iointly in founding the Gospell, wihtout all malice or clamorous strife. Afterwards wee finde this holy zeale no whit abated; still in succeeding times, as perfecutions waxt hotter, the Christians loue grew more enflamed. To manifest which, least it might lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish if conceal'd, how many signes of expression had they? witnesse there <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or feasts of loue: there <hi>os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum pacis</hi> after their sacred meetings: yea <hi>osculum baptismi</hi> at their admittance into the Church: lastly their <hi>panem vnanimitatis,</hi> as <hi>Paulinus</hi> to <hi>Austin</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateth; a token commonly annext and sent with their letters to expresse their ioint consolidation into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26776:25"/> the same body of Christ; As for hatred and malice, such vngodly motions, they may seeme as free, as we their of-spring now stand guilty.</p>
            <p>Yet what wonder is it if thus reciprocally they maintained charity? For first (you know) among all virtues this takes place: without it <hi>martyr dome</hi> it selfe availeth not, 1. Cor. 13. <hi>Lumbard</hi> so farre extols it, as to make it touching the exercise an immediate act of the spirit: whereas other divine graces acknowledge their proper habits. How truely he doth this I meane not to examine; only you see what a glorious conceit he had of this vertue aboue the rest.</p>
            <p>Againe, such loue greatly strengthens each where the Christian zeale: it conserues as it were religion warme and frolick. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epistle to the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians</hi> discoursing to this purpose, tells them that it would keepe them more secure euen from Satans as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saults; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. all assronts (saith he) of those spirituall enimyes be this way lessened: ioine they but hearts, sinne it selfe would finde an harder inlet.</p>
            <p>Once more, no marvaile if <hi>orthodox</hi> Christians af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect this concord, since our Saviour himselfe so much commends it; whenas hee who is the author of peace appeares so vrgent a teacher thereof. In the 13. of Io. he makes it the very marke and badge of his: <hi>By this shall all men knowe that you are my Disciples, &amp;.</hi> v. 35 In the 14. C. being now to suffer, he bequeaths it them for their only legacy, <hi>My peace I leaue you,</hi> v. 27. with great earnestnesse he enioines that, which long since was commended to the Church vnder a type; <hi>Noahs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26776:26"/> done</hi> hauing circled the waters too and fro, returnes not empty; yet brings shee for a token of the floods decrease, no other testimony into the arke, the figure of the Church, then an <hi>Oliue</hi> lease; a leafe which is the vsuall signe of loue and concord; hence the Apostle more expresly, Rom. 10. 15. deciphers the Church vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der name of the <hi>Oliue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You perceiue by this a little better the fowlnesse of <hi>Schismes:</hi> how vgly they be apart, yet more if oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to <hi>vnity:</hi> giue mee now leaue but to set downe some few rules, as well for the aduancing of the one, as the repressing of the other, and I will end.</p>
            <p>First then, it were well if men did meddle lesse in needlesse points besides the saith: were they not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busie there, where they may shew more wit, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Gospell. The orthodox religion stands now betwixt <hi>Papistry</hi> and <hi>Semi-polagianisme,</hi> as the Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke sect did once betweene the Epicureans and the<note place="margin">Acodemicarū Quaestionum. L. 2.</note> Stoicks; <hi>cum his non de finibus sed de tota fere possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one contentio est;</hi> with these, saith the <hi>Oratgur,</hi> the Platonicks hold an vtter distance; but from them they differ vpon tearmes of lighter moment. Papistrie thwarts and cuts the very life-strings of a sauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. Semi-pelagianisme no so; whence then the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test danger appeares, there to bee most actiue were a prudent course.</p>
            <p>Or 2<seg rend="sup">ly</seg>, if some must needs be dealing else-where, would they could but keepe their opinions conceal'd; not presse vpon the Church for currant whatsoeuer themselues haue fancied; <hi>Paracelsus</hi> hauing grounded himselfe strongly in naturall <hi>magicke,</hi> afterward in all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26776:26"/> his conclusions ascribes ouer much to that; with him <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; <hi>Methuselah</hi> liued so long not without some helpe of <hi>Chymicall</hi> extracts; Vpon like grounds <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi>
               <note place="margin">De occults Philos. L. 4.</note> among others his foppish notions, perswades vs, that the crosse if of force at all, it is by vertue of the meer figure. Mē for the most part relish long of those principles with which they haue beene at first invred. The vnderstainding is so farre from embracing the opposite truth, that it rests and scarcely admits of a farther search. Moreouer, and what they haue once conceipted priuately, they straight way labour to make good a broad; hold they cannot, but they will obtrude their peculiar fancies, for a publike trueth; Our sauiour <hi>Math.</hi> 16. speaking of such doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> calls it <hi>leauen</hi> v. 6. Euen as leauen it heaues &amp; workes in the braine till it can get a vent; Much discreeter was the course of Saint <hi>Cyprian;</hi> The deuout father being vnhappily tainted in that point concerning <hi>Anabaptisme,</hi> yet would he by no meanes commemd it for a classicke tenent; <hi>nemini prescribi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp;c.</hi> let others (saith hee) abound in a contrary sence: for my part I aduise none: which his modesty if diuerse now adaies did follow, from how many vnnecessary tumults might they secure the Church.</p>
            <p>But suppose a <hi>Schisme</hi> be once on foote, the spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diest way for redresse may seeme; First a serious yet ciuill debatement: when men shall enter the lists as willing to yeeld, if pechance convinc'd, as to refuse the assaylant'; hot and furious disputes doe seldome good; amidst the noise of such conuiciating iarres, the the truth is scarcely heard. The discussion of doubtfull
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26776:27"/> points resembles much the smiting of a <hi>flint;</hi> a gentle and well poys'de stroke procures some sparkes; whereas a boisterous collision, gets no fire, but breakes the stone; Iust so in point of controversie: a civill hadling brings it to an issue straight; contrariwise an impetuous wrangling inflicts happily some staine on either party, yet nothing cleeres the argument. Vnwisely then deale they who fly out into such a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempered vehemency; Insteed of a sober and vsefull debatement they raise a personall brawle; they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse not at length the truth, but their owne cause. It was the noted fault of <hi>Marcellus</hi> a <hi>Rhetoritian</hi> that<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> lighting on a figure, hee would pursue it so farre, till he had forgot the matter in hand: likewise doe these if once they fall into a calumniating &amp; iarring vaine; nay farther, oft times, they strangely misinterpret the aduersary; either to extend their discourse, or else of malice they impose a meaning farre wide from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors drift. Thus as <hi>Eebul</hi> told <hi>Goal, Thou seest the shadowes of mountaines as if they were men, Iudg.</hi> 9. 36. they bestow much fruitlesse paines in confuting such notions as themselues haue fram'de amisse. But away with such misprison: such rouing encounters; it is a more probable course, if, as I said, they neither shall ouer roughly dispute the cause, nor yet suspiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously make it worse.</p>
            <p>A second helpe here may bee the vse of <hi>Synodicall</hi> conuents: conuents which are no lesse apt to represse falshood, then establish a receiued truth in the mindes of people. The Romans of old when any more fatall danger approached, did wontedly maintaine their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26776:27"/> standing <hi>Senate;</hi> how much rather in a Christian state appeares some like proiect needfull: where sinne and error make a daily inrode. Our forefathers therefore of the primitiue Church, may seeme indeede in such meetings very frequent; euery yeare twice, about <hi>Lent</hi> and <hi>antumne</hi> they ordained councels provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be held. Hereby they weeded as it were and cut vp errour in its first appearance: no sooner could it sprout forth, before it procured strength, some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree or other straight waies cropt it; Satan you know that old <hi>Serpent</hi> is the father of schismes: nay he was by a voluntary discession from God simply the prime <hi>Schismaticke;</hi> A snake or serpent if he can get but his head into a crany, scrues &amp; wreaths in his whole body after with no hard paine: on this manner error; by reason of its <hi>Serpentine</hi> nature, vnlesse at first repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, threatens a dangerous progresse; Councels then in this case be greatly available; of loueraine helpe, if thus seasonably applied; such a meeting of reuerent sages must needs if not refell, at least discountenance a crept in falshood.</p>
            <p>The last remedy shall bee a serious aduise; That men would duely consider how by <hi>Schismes</hi> they would afresh the body of Christ; how they make the wonted fold a coate of raueuing wolues. <hi>Hermes</hi> somewhere termes malitiousnesse <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the foode or worlds repast; let not, oh let not the same be said concerning the <hi>Church</hi> it selfe; Weigh likewise hereto the vnknowne and doubtfull euent of such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, The <hi>Collator</hi> in Prosper begins fairely and as a moderate <hi>pelagian,</hi> but ere three pages are past lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26776:28"/>
               <hi>Pelagianisme,</hi> he becomes flat <hi>Atheist.</hi> Vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestary disputes neuer remaine in that state of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in which they were at first raised; like floods they gaine encrease from their continued and lasting course; especially if there happen (though I hope not) such as dispense them secretly &amp; of purpose to some farther end: When <hi>Hannibal</hi> mainely intended Rome he tooke in <hi>Saguntum</hi> (saith the <hi>historian</hi>) onely by the way; for occasion-sake in truth of a desired warre;<note place="margin">Liuie.</note> God grant there be none who beginne at these lower points, that they may sight at length not against Rome, but for it.</p>
            <p>I haue done with my text; a subiect I confesse some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to high for me, and deseruing a more graue and learned pen; such an one wherein they sho<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld chiefly labour, who are as able for skill, as effectuall in power and place. Truth is then most persuasiue, when thus abetted: but as <hi>Elihu</hi> tooke courage to aduise <hi>Iob,</hi> though after his elders: <hi>to shew his opinion also; Iob.</hi> 22. v. 10. euen so haue I done. Wisdome is of God, and oft times hee worketh no lesse through weake meanes, then by strong and potent. Howsoeuer I thought it not besides the duety of the meanest <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,</hi> if now he stretcht forth his hand to vpholde the <hi>arke:</hi> if for my part likewise I endeauourde the Churches <hi>vnity,</hi> my only drift. And now O Lord doe thou build vp those <hi>breaches</hi> in the <hi>wals</hi> of our Ierusalem, which by <hi>Schismes</hi> haue long since beene made; giue vs externall peace, that so the better wee may procure that inward of minde, and in fine enioy eternall with thee. To God the Father, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26776:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>